The Cape of Good Hope.On Africa's southerly tip.
好望角 位于非洲南端
Here two great seas meet,
两大洋在这里汇合
one,the warm Indian Ocean,
一个是温暖的印度洋
the other the chilly Atlantic.
另一个是寒冷的大西洋
And as they mingle,so they create a billowing cloak
在两大洋汇合之下,风起云涌
that drapes the summit of Table Mountain.
桌山之巅雪雾缥缈
Spectacular though this is,
景色如斯壮丽
the mountain's cloudy covering is only a hint of the profound influence
其实暗示着...
that these two very different oceans have on the fortunes of life here.
两大洋对区内生态的深远影响
And not just here at the Cape
不只限于好望角
but across the length and breadth of Southern Africa.
而是整个非洲南部
好望角
解说人:大卫・艾登堡
Two thousand miles north from the Cape,
好望角以北2000英里之外
beneath this sandy beach,new life is stirring.
在这沙滩下,新生命蠢蠢欲动
Hundreds of baby green turtles emerge like a torrent,
数以百计的小小绿海龟
from the safety of their nest.
从安全的龟巢涌出
Each one,just seven centimetres long,
每一只身长不过7厘米
但现在疾走100米冲下沙滩 must make a hundred－metre sprint down the beach.
From the moment they hatch,
从孵化一刻开始
they're driven by an instinctive urge to run to the sea.
它们便受本能驱使,向海洋奔去
Few creatures start life with the odds for success so heavily stacked against them.
很少生物一出世便遇上如此大敌
Yellow billed kites.
黄嘴鸢
Pied crows.
非洲白颈鸦
But so many of these hatchlings appear together,
但由于大量小龟同时涌现
that predators can't catch them all.
掠食者一时应接不暇
Last out,this baby might seem doomed.
最后离巢的小龟似乎难逃一死
But struggling out late could just give her a chance.
但押后现身又可能反而有生机
The crows seem insatiable.
非洲白颈鸦似乎怎么吃也不饱
Even those that reach the sea aren't safe.
就连游进海里的小龟也不能幸免
This female has to make a dash for it.
这只雌龟要急急逃命
She's still in danger and not just from above.
危机仍在,而且不只来自天空
A Ghost crab may be smaller than the hatchling,
鬼蟹体形虽然小于小龟
but it has the strength to drag her into its lair.
但有力把它拖入蟹窝
Not this time.
今次落空了
At last, the sea.
终于到了大海
She has to catch a breath if she's not to drown,
它必须吸口气,才不至淹死
but the pounding waves make it desperately difficult.
但在海浪冲击下,很难做到
Beyond the surf,calmer water,
在碎浪带之外,海面较为平静
but even here the hatchling is not out of danger.
但就算在这里,小龟仍未脱离险境
She dives.
它向下潜
Just in time.
及时逃过大难
Only one hatchling in a thousand will survive to adulthood,
每千只小龟只有一只可以长成
but if she does,she may live for 80 years.
成功的话,可以活到80岁
For now,the ocean is there to be explored.
现时,整个海洋任它闯荡
As the hatchling disappears into the deep blue,
小龟消失在深海之中
she swims into the waters of one of the planet's most powerful currents:
它游进了地球一大洋流:
the Agulhas.
阿加勒斯海流
The Agulhas sweeps south towards the Cape,
阿加勒斯海流向南流往好望角
transporting a hundred billion gallons of warm water every day.
每天输送1000亿加仑暖水
These tropical seas are so warm,
热带海洋温度甚高
they evaporate on an enormous scale.
大量的海水蒸发
Water vapour rises until at altitude it cools
水蒸气上升,然后在高空冷却
and condenses into clouds.
凝成云层
As the clouds drift inland,,
云层飘向内陆
they bring rain to one of the least explored corners of our planet.
为一个荒僻角落带来雨水
The mountains of Mozambique.
莫桑比克山脉
This the wettest place in Southern Africa.
这是非洲南部雨水最多的地区
Decades of civil war have kept travellers away from this little known land.
数十年内战,令外人难以踏足
It was satellite mapping
全靠人造卫星测绘
that revealed the full extent of the forest that grows here,
揭露这大片森林的全貌
so now it's known to outsiders as the "Google" rainforest.
所以外界把这里称为Google雨林
It could also be called the butterfly forest.
这里也可以称为蝴蝶林
After the rains,butterflies have emerged together in huge numbers.
在雨后,大批蝴蝶聚集
As soon as their wings dry out,
翅膀干了之后,
they will take to the air.
便振翅高飞
Their goal,to find a mate.
它们志在求偶
But how?
但怎进行呢?
There may be thousands close by but the foliage is so thick,
附近可能有成千上万的同类
it's difficult for them to find each other.
但树木浓密,不容易遇上
They have a remarkable solution.
它们有个别开生面的解决办法
They follow rivers upstream and travel to higher ground.
它们沿河流而上,往高处飞去
The journey can take hours of determined flying.
可能要坚定不移地飞行多个小时
Eventually,they emerge into the only open space there is.
终于它们到达唯一的空旷地方
The treeless peak of Mount Mabu.
没有树木的麻布山顶峰
Up here,free from the confines of the forest,
在山顶,它们不再受制于雨林
they hold a butterfly ball.
便举行蝴蝶舞会
Now the butterflies have all the space they need for their aerobatic courtship.
这里有空间施展杂耍式的追求大法
The male's strategy is simple:
雄蝶的策略很简单:
fly higher and faster than the competition
只要比对手飞得更高、更快
and just maybe you'll win a virgin female.
便有机会夺得美蝶归
This spectacular gathering unseen by outsiders until now,
外界首次有缘目睹这种美丽聚会
happens for just half an hour each morning
每年只有短短数星期时间
and for just a few weeks in the year.
在早上出现半个小时
Once mated,the females descend back to the rainforest to lay their eggs.
雌蝶交配后,便飞回雨林生蛋
A forest that only exists,
而雨林之所以存在
because of moisture rising from the warm Agulhas current,
皆因数百英里外的印度洋
hundreds of miles away in the Indian Ocean.
有个温暖的阿加勒斯海流带来湿气
The rainwater now flows southwards from Mozambique's highest peaks,
雨水从莫桑比克山巅向南流动
to the lowlands of the Eastern Cape.
到达好望角东部的低地
And where the land flattens,
土地渐渐平坦,
rivers slow,
河水速度减慢
creating a vast swamp 50 miles across.
形成一个宽50英里的大沼泽
This is Gorongosa.
这里是戈龙戈萨
Here all kinds of creatures come to catch fish.
各种动物都跑来捕鱼
Whiskered catfish work as a team.
长须鲶鱼分工合作
They take a gulp of air at the surface and then belch it out underwater,
它们在水面吸气,在水底喷出
to create a net of bubbles.
形成一团气泡
And that traps little fish.
把小鱼困住
There are fish for everyone.
这里鱼量丰富,谁也不愁吃
And each species has its own technique for catching them.
每种动物各有一套捕鱼大法
It's all very well having a big beak but you've still got to know how to use it.
有个大喙是好事,但也要善用
This young pelican has a lot to learn,
年轻的鹈鹕尚要好好学习
and not long to do so.
而且时间无多
Maybe,like the catfish,teamwork is the answer.
或者要学鲶鱼一样分工合作
It's certainly working for the flock
鹈鹕群似乎大有收获
and this pelican seems to be getting the hang of it.
年轻鹈鹕似乎开始掌握到窍门
But surely,he can't swallow that catfish?
但它只怕吞不下这尾鲶鱼吧?
Trying to was a mistake.
它太冒进,犯了大错
The rainwater,briefly held in Gorongosa's swamp,
在戈龙戈萨沼泽短暂停留的雨水
has now been enriched with silt and sand.
带着肥沃的淤泥和沙土离开
这些堆满沉积物的河[Sandian] All down this coast, sediment－laden rivers,
the Zambezi,the Limpopo,the Save
赞比西河、林波波河、萨韦河
drain back to the sea,
缓缓流回大海
and there they meet the Agulhas current.
与阿加勒斯海流汇合
And what happens to all that sand?
大量的沙土跑往哪里呢?
Over the millennia,the Agulhas has worked it
经过阿加勒斯海流冲刷了千百年
into a complex underwater landscape.
形成错综复杂的海底环境
This vast sand sculpture is the Bazaruto Archipelago,
这片大沙土名为巴扎鲁托群岛
the oldest of its kind in the world.
历史最悠久
It may look like paradise but living here is not easy.
看来似天堂,其实不易居
For a hundred thousand years,the Agulhas Current
阿加勒斯海流造成的沙暴
has battered these submerged dunes with underwater sandstorms.
在10万年来不停冲击这些水底沙丘
But where the water is deep enough to escape these storms,
但在不受沙暴冲击的深水处
nutrients carried from Africa's interior
凝聚了来自非洲内陆的养份
fuel an explosion of life.
万物欣欣向荣
A rare oceanic hunter rules here.
这里有位罕见的海洋猎者
Giant kingfish.
珍
As big as a man and weight for weight,
体形大如男子
one of the most powerful fish in the sea.
是最孔武有力的海鱼之一
Despite their size,they're extraordinarily agile when hunting.
虽然体形大,猎食时十分敏捷
Normally, kingfish are solitary,
珍通常孤单独行
but for just a few weeks each year,
但每年有三数星期
they gather at places like Bazaruto
便在巴扎鲁托这类地方聚集
and prepare for an extraordinary journey.
准备踏上不寻常的旅途
One that will take them far inland.
行程会深入内陆
The Mtentu River.
丹图河
The king of kingfish leads them upstream.
珍之王带领鱼群往上游
As they travel further into freshwater,
它们游进淡水的水域
they seem to change from aggressive hunters into dedicated pilgrims.
似乎不再是猎者,而是虔诚朝圣者
Now,many miles from their natural home,
它们远离自然栖息地
and in response to an unknown cue,
在某种未明朗的呼召下
they stop and begin to circle.
它们停下来、并开始旋转
Other marine fish that migrate upriver
其他迁徙至上游水域的海鱼
usually do so in order to breed,
通常志在繁殖
but there's no evidence that these kingfish spawn up here.
但珍没有留下产卵的迹象
Neither do they hunt.
它们也不猎食
So,what are they doing?
那么,它们在做什么?
In truth,the purpose of this strange behaviour is still unknown.
事实上没人知道这奇异行为的目的
Within a few weeks,they will retrace their journey back to the ocean.
数星期之内,它们便折回大海
The lives of kingfish,
珍的生命
like those of turtles and butterflies and pelicans,
就像海龟、蝴蝶、鹈鹕一样
are influenced by the Agulhas Current.
受到阿加勒斯海流影响
But that influence can only reach so far,
但海流的影响力也有一定局限
and this is why.
原因就在这里
The Drakensberg Mountains.
德拉肯斯堡山脉
Here,local people say that the vultures soar so high,
本地人说这里的兀鹫可直冲云霄
they can see into the future.
看到未来
These sheer cliffs,rising to over 3,000 metres,
这些峭壁耸立在3000米之上
hold back the advancing rain clouds
挡住了雨云的去路
and as a result,the land beyond them is starved of water.
于是山脉以外的土地便缺水
This is the greatest expanse of sand in the world.
这是世上最大的沙漠
A seemingly endless desert that is the vast parched centre of Southern Africa.
一望无际的荒漠,在非洲南部中心
Thousands of miles to the west,
往西数千英里外
where this desert meets the Atlantic Ocean,
沙漠与大西洋接坏之处
another current prevails.
有另一股海流
But the Benguela Current,surging up the west side of Africa,
但这股在非洲西面的本格拉海流
has a very different character.
却有截然不同的特性
It's extremely cold,full of nutrients
它是一股寒流、养份丰足
and it's thronged with life.
水域内生机蓬勃
A great white shark.
大白鲨
They can raise their body temperature
它们可以把体温提高
to 10 degrees above that of the surrounding sea.
比周围的水温高出10度
但需要动用大量高级燃料 But doing so requires an enormous amount of high－grade fuel.
So,this is a great bonanza for them,the body of a dead whale.
所以鲸尸是受欢迎的大餐
The carcass will draw in every great white for miles around.
鲸尸把周围的大白鲨都引来
And here,off Cape Town,that means a lot of sharks.
而开普敦对外水域有很多鲨鱼
Instead of feeding in a frenzy,
它们不是疯狂抢食
these sharks have rather refined table manners.
这些鲨鱼十分讲究餐桌礼仪
它们肩并肩游过,互相较量体型 They swim side－by－side to get the measure of each other.
Then,each takes its turn.
然后大家轮流进食
This female is the biggest so she eats first.
这尾雌鲨体形最大,所以先吃
The next only feeds when she gives way.
等它让路,下一尾才开始进食
The waters of the Benguela are so rich,
由于本格拉海流的水域养份丰富
they support more great white sharks than any other seas on the planet.
大白鲨数量冠全球
And they are so cold,
而且海水冰冻
they attract some surprising creatures to these African shores.
一些难得的访客也被引来非洲海岸
Penguins.
企鹅
African Penguins.
非洲企鹅
This female is returning to relieve her partner.
这只雌企鹅回来接替配偶
Of course,there's no ice here
这里当然没有冰
but these rocks can be almost as slippery.
但岩石也几乎一样湿滑
But there are more serious obstacles than the slippery rocks awaiting them.
除了湿滑岩石,还有更大的障碍
It's his turn to feed
现在轮到雄企鹅觅食
so he leaves her to look after their eggs.
它把照顾鹅蛋的责任交给雌企鹅
Now,she must tackle a problem faced by no other kind of penguin.
雌企鹅面对的问题与其他企鹅不同
For the next 10 days,she must protect her eggs from the African sun.
未来10天它要替鹅蛋摭档非洲烈日
A dense coat of feathers that keeps her warm in cold seas now stifles her.
可抵挡冰洋的厚羽毛令它透不过气
On these exposed rocks,
在露天的岩石上
she must shade her eggs instead of keeping them warm.
它替鹅蛋挡开阳光,不需要保温
Everything here seems the wrong way round.
这里的情况似乎完全反常
For some,the soaring temperature is too much.
有一些企鹅熬不住高温
A neighbour deserts his nest.
有位邻居弃巢而去
His egg will not survive.
它的蛋肯定死路一条
He's not the only one to give up,
它不是唯一的逃兵
some years,not a single chick is reared.
有些年头,一只幼企鹅也孵不出来
Penguins are adapted to withstand temperatures of 40 degrees below zero
企鹅适应零下40度的低温
not 40 degrees above.
熬不住40度高温
Now,at the hottest part of the day,the very worst time,
就在最炎热、最艰难的时刻
her chicks are hatching.
雌企鹅的蛋开始孵化
Just when they need her most,
就在幼雏最需要它的时刻
she's reaching the limit of her endurance.
它到了容忍的极限
After 10 days of intensive fishing,
企鹅爸爸专心捕鱼十天
the chicks' father comes back to take his turn at the nest.
现在回来鹅巢当值
But will he be too late?
但会否来迟一步?
He greets his young for the very first time.
它第一次见到自己的子女
The coolness of the Benguela Current brought the penguins here
本格拉海流是寒流,所以引来企鹅
but that very coolness is a great disadvantage
但寒凉的特性也带来不利
because it generates little rain.
因为雨水少
It can,however,produce moisture in a different form.
不过海流以另一方式制造湿气
A thick blanket of fog rolls in from the sea
厚厚的雾从海洋卷入
and condenses on this thirsty land.
在这片缺水的土地上凝聚
And each year,the desert bursts into life with a dazzling display.
每一年,沙漠都会突然百花齐放
Water is so scarce that this show will not last long
由于缺水,花卉展览并不长久
so plants compete to attract their pollinators,with colour.
植物必须努力色诱动物来传播花粉
Here in Namaqualand,a 600-mile strip of coastal desert
纳马夸兰是长600英里的海岸沙漠
becomes carpeted with blooms.
这里繁花似锦
The morning sun opens a Namaqua Daisy
纳马雏菊迎着早晨的阳光开花
and reveals a male monkey beetle asleep inside.
原来有只雄性猴甲虫睡在花内
Nights here are so cold
由于晚上太冷
that monkey beetles shelter within the closed up petals of the daisies.
猴甲虫躲在雏菊合上的花瓣内避寒
The habit brings benefits to both sides.
这个习惯对双方都有好处
The beetle is kept warm and the flower gets pollinated.
猴甲虫可保暖,花粉又可以传播
But now the beetle has urgent business.He must find a mate.
但现在它有件急务: 求偶
As he searches,he hops from bloom to bloom pollinating each in turn.
寻觅期间,它在花间跳跃传粉
At last,he spots a potential mate.
终于它找到对象
A golden princess.
金黄的公主
But here comes trouble.
但麻烦来了
A rival.
有对手
There's no time for introductions.
没有时间谈情说爱了
But he's been too slow.
但它动作太慢了
The rivals immediately begin to brawl.
情敌相遇,立即打斗起来
The female will only mate inside the daisy
雌猴甲虫只在雏菊内交配
so they wrestle for possession.
所以它们要抢夺有利阵地
They're so engrossed in fighting,
它们只顾打斗,
they've pushed her off.
把雌性推了下去
The challenger is ejected.
挑战者被赶走
The winner wastes no time before getting back to business.
胜利者立即继续办正事
At last!
终于得偿所愿!
Now,there will be a new generation of monkey beetles
现在又有了新一代的猴甲虫
to pollinate these Namaqualand flowers.
为纳马旁蔺的花朵传播花粉
For most of the year,
年中大部分时间,
this land is desperately dry
土地都极度干旱
but just occasionally,brief,violent storms sweep in from the cold ocean.
但偶有短暂的暴风从冰冷海洋刮来
Springbok have been roaming this desert for many months,
跳羚在沙漠上游荡了数月
searching for one of these rare and highly localised downpours.
追寻难得、只在局部地区落下的雨
The grass is sprouting.
草正开始发芽
And that is worth celebrating.
实在值得庆祝!
If you're a springbok,
如果你是跳羚,
that means pranking.
便会跳跃起来
We still don't know exactly why they do this.
我们仍未知道它们因何这样做
The simplest answer is that they're dancing for joy.
最简单的解释是: 它们跳舞作乐
Africa's most southerly tip.
非洲的最南端
This is where the two great ocean currents,
温暖的阿加勒斯海流
the warm Agulhas and the cold Benguela,
和寒冷的本格拉海流
crash into one another.
在此交汇
And this collision in itself draws in life in abundance.
吸引了大量生物聚集
A super pod of hunting dolphins 5,000 strong.
由5000只海豚组成的大猎队
And shadowing them,
而跟在后面的...
Africa's biggest predator.
是非洲最巨大的掠食者[Sandian]
A Bryde's whale.
布氏鲸
This female is 15 metres long
这尾雌鲸身长15米
and weighs more than a whole family of elephants.
比整个大象家族更要重
The dolphins are in pursuit of sardines,millions of them!
海豚在追踪数以百万计的沙丁鱼
But these cold water fish are heading towards
这些冷水鱼正游向...
an impenetrable barrier of warm water
难以越过的暖水区
that they will not cross,the Agulhas Current.
是它们不会越涡的阿加勒斯海流
They're trapped.
它们被困了
And that gives the whale her chance.
于是鲸鱼的机会来了
But the sardines are so speedy
但沙丁鱼身手敏捷
that the whale only catches a few with each pass.
鲸鱼每次只能捕捉三数尾鱼
More and more hunters arrive.
越来越多猎者到场
The whale needs the other hunters to push the fish upwards,
鲸鱼需要其他猎者帮忙
forcing them against the surface.
把沙丁鱼迫近水面
Now,they have nowhere to escape.
现在它们再也无路可逃
With each lumbering turn,she loses precious time,
鲸鱼转身缓慢,损失宝贵时间
time that favours the more nimble.
这样对敏捷的对手比较有利
The Bryde's whale probably knows
布氏鲸可能知道
that this opportunity will last less than five minutes
这个机会只持续不足5分钟
and with the last few lunges,
它再猛扑数次,
she finally cashes in.
终于可以开怀大嚼
The forces that triggered this great event have also shaped the fortunes
除了在这个战场引发这壮观场面外
of life far beyond this particular battleground.
海流的动力也影响了远处的生物
Without these currents,Southern Africa would be a desert.
没这些海流,非洲南部便变成荒漠
But combined,the very different powers of the Agulhas and the Benguela
但阿加勒斯和本格拉两大海流发功
have transformed the Cape into a land where life can flourish.
把好望角变成生机蓬勃的好地方
翻译：张丽莉
非洲 零距离
The Comoro Islands of Africa's east coast
非洲东海岸的科摩罗群岛
are a haven for green turtles.
是绿海龟的天堂
Every year,a million turtles hatch on these beaches,
海滩上每年都有上百万只小海龟孵化
but the chances of any one of them surviving is tiny.
但它们的个体生存率却极低
The Africa team came here to try and capture the dramatic
摄制组的任务是前来拍摄
first few minutes in the lives of these baby turtles.
小海龟们出生时那戏剧性的一幕
It was to be both a technical,
那不仅是对摄影技术
and surprisingly emotional challenge.
也是对情感的一次挑战
It's only when you get down on the eye level of the baby turtle
只有当你站在小海龟的视角
that you realise what an enormous journey it's got to make
你才能意识到  爬出沙滩
down over the beach,and it really is quite epic.
是场如此浩大的史诗般旅程
That's fine.Oh,yeah,that's lovely.
好的  真可爱
It's using all these complicated,heavy bits of equipment
借助这些复杂且沉重的设备
which hopefully will enable us to get into the world of
我们能够切身地体会到
休・皮尔森 制片人
a turtle which is just a few inches long.
只有几英汲さ男『９
As they break out of all the soft sand,they hit the hard sand
它们先爬过软沙滩  后爬上硬沙滩
and that's where the real sprint takes place.
然后它们开始全力冲刺
They must be desperate to hit that water,
它们一定迫不及待地希望进入海中
because you can see the sea's just over the horizon.
因为你可以看到大海就在地平线处
We're following them all the way down
我们一直跟随着它们
and you do kind of get involved with them and cheering them on.
情不自禁地为它们加油打气
OK,slow down a bit.Slow down.
慢一点  放慢速度
And suddenly all these crows come flocking in
突然  乌鸦成群结队地飞来
and start picking them off
开始将它们一个个叼走
and you just think,that's just so unfair.
你会觉得太不公平
Lots more coming in.Just loads coming in now.
乌鸦越来越多  铺天盖地地飞落下来
I do,God,I feel for them.
天呐  我很难过
You know it's really quite upsetting
那太令人苦恼了
and particularly when you're looking through the camera
特别是当你全身心将镜头
and I'm just filling frame with a turtle running down the beach,
聚焦着一只奋力爬出海滩的小海龟
then suddenly from nowhere,
突然不知从哪儿
a beak comes in and whoosh,that's it.
伸出一只鸟嘴  完了
That turtle's no more.
小海龟没了
The turtles that escape the perils of the beach
小海龟们逃脱了海滩上的危机
still have to face pounding surf.
接踵而来是海浪的重击
But,at last,they're in their element.
但最终它们如鱼得水般获救
More than can be said for the crew.
对摄制组而言就没那么幸运了
－它们游得比你快  对吧  －是的 － They're faster than you, aren't they?  － Yep.
It's a bit embarrassing.
有点难堪
Beaten by something that's less than a day old.
被出生未够一天的小东西打败了
When you see hatchlings get off the beach and going in the white water,
当你看着小海龟离开沙滩  游入泛白的海水
休・米勒 摄影师
you'd think they'd just get obliterated.
你会以为它们被海水吞没了
They just punch through the water; they do get flung around
它们努力划水  不停被水流冲击
but then they just right themselves,
但它们很快调整了姿态
keep on swimming and they're ahead of you,
继续游  并且游在你前面
coming out the back of the wave
最后出现在海浪的背面
and it's amazing.
那太神奇了
You're seeing all these baby turtles getting picked off,
小海龟被海浪冲得失去了方向
left,right and centre,but they just keep going.
左右晃动  但它们从未停止前行
They are just so resilient.
它们迅速就恢复了活力
And that made what happened next so distressing.
但接下来发生的事着实令人悲痛
A particularly high spring tide flooded the beach.
一波超高的海浪涌上沙滩
Any baby turtles still in their nests
尚被埋在巢穴深处的小海龟
would be lucky to survive.
能否幸存就得看运气了
－瞧  水中冒着泡泡  －是的 － See it bubbling out as well. － Yeah.
It means that basically anything below that line's going to be gone.
那意味着水位线下的所有东西都将被海水带走
Let's hope and pray it's not,
让我们祈祷不会...
but...
但是...
As you say,we don't know,let's wait and see.
正如你所说的  让我们拭目以待吧
All across the world,turtles are in decline.
全球海龟数量正在减少
Their eggs are stolen,
龟蛋被偷
the adults are hunted for their flesh
捕捉成年龟作肉食
and they drown in fishing nets.
它们自己则常常陷落渔网
But here in the Comoros,they have friends.
但在科摩罗  幸有救星在
It's amazing here in Itsamia.
伊兹米亚真是个伟大的地方
It's just a really heartening story of
此处上演着温暖人心的故事
how the local people are doing everything they can
当地人都竭尽全力
to protect sort of what they think of as their turtles.
用自己的方式来保护海龟
And some of the baby turtles have survived the flood tide.
使有些小海龟在涨潮中幸免于难
我已经在巢里
找到了两只小海龟
如果我们保住了巢
就帮它们离开
这里是我的村子
我得保护这些小海龟
和成年龟
那是为了我们所有人
The whole village comes to help the hatchlings.
所有村民都会帮助这些刚孵化的小家伙们
But the most important effort is to protect the adults
但最重要的是保护成年海龟
from outsiders who would hunt them for their meat.
不被外人猎杀取肉
They've taken it upon themselves to really police the beaches around here
他们主动承担保护沙滩的责任
and make sure that poaching is kept to a minimum.
将非法偷猎行为减到最低程度
The selfless protection these people provide means
那些人提供的无私保护
that this is one of the few places in the world
使得这里的海龟数量成为
where turtle numbers are actually increasing.
全球少有出现增长的地区之一
And remarkably,here in Itsamia,
最棒的是  在伊兹米亚
the population has in fact doubled in the last decade.
海龟数量在过去10年中翻了一番
As the shoot was coming to the end,
在拍摄即将结束时
cameraman Kevin Flay noticed that
摄影师凯文・弗莱注意到
some of the turtles that made it through the surf faced one last danger.
成功越过海浪的小海龟 面临最后一道考验
I'm getting shots of a kite which is flying down
我拍到一只鸢飞下来
and taking turtles off the water surface.
从海面上将小龟叼走
That was a part of the story we had to tell.
那情景我们必须呈现
The aim is for us to be underwater,looking straight up as this happens,
当拍摄鸢飞来抓小海龟时 镜头需由水底往上瞄准
and that's actually really quite hard.
其实还挺有难度的
OK. Three, two, one...
好  3  2  1
Undeterred,the crew got into position.
摄制人员各就各位 迎难而上
There we go,the kite's up.
来了  鸢起飞
You can't see where you're going
我看不见前进方向
because my head's glued to this viewfinder,
因为我的头和取景器连在一起
so I'm banging into rocks and things like that.
所以我会偶尔撞上石头之类的东西
I'm really just trying to keep the turtle in shot.
我一直尽力让小海龟的身影保持在镜头里
Something came in then.
此时不知何物飞过来
She came in and swooped down over the water's surface.
它俯冲而下掠过水面
And you could see the kite from underwater?
你在水下能看到那只鸢吗?
I could see it,I could see the shape.
能看到  并且看清形状
－都拍到了吗?  －没错 － In frame and you were running? － Yep.
－但没抓到海龟  －没抓到 － Didn't take the turtle. － Didn't take the turtle.
Probably that's the best of both worlds,
双赢最好不过
because we got our lovely underwater shot of a kite
我们在水下拍到了鸢
and the turtle gets away!
小海龟也得以逃脱
This lucky hatchling isn't the only one.
眼前的小海龟并非唯一幸运儿
With the help of the village of Itsamia,
在伊兹米亚村民的帮助下
thousands more have a chance to make it to the open ocean.
数千只小海龟得以投入海洋的怀抱
It's only really local populations that can actually support
也只有当地群众才能真正支持
and sustain this conservation work.
并长期做动物保育工作
If it comes from the roots upwards,
只有从草根做起
then it's got a chance of success.
才能取得长久保育成功
You know,I think it's amazing,I really do,
我觉得真的很棒  真的
the fact that they do this and you know
能坚持做这些
we should see it more often around the world.
要是世界各地都能这样就好了
It's hard not to admire these extraordinary little creatures
看到这些非凡的小生物与命运抗争
as they battle against such odds.
我们很难不佩服
This baby turtle won't touch land again
眼前的小海龟再次踏上陆地时
until she returns to the very same island to lay her own eggs.
将是返回同一座岛屿产卵的时候
With luck,she'll find the beach
幸运的话  它将发现这片海滩
still protected by the people of Itsamia.
依旧受伊兹米亚人民保护着
Next time,the vast cauldron of the Sahara Desert.
下集我们将走入撒哈拉沙漠这座大火炉
这片占据了整个非洲大陆三分之一面积的广袤荒野 This colossal wilderness covers one－third of the entire African continent.
To survive here,life is stretched to its very limits.
在这里生存需要挑战极限
Simply being tough isn't enough.
顽强还远远不够
Only the most extraordinary creatures will triumph.
只有最非凡的生物才能幸存